A Guide to the Patrick Henry Drewry Papers, 1825-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Patrick Henry Drewry Papers 1825-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8255
This collection consists of ca. 16,500 items, 23 shelf feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers and correspondence of the Drewry Collection were received on deposit 9 May 1966 from John Metcalf Drewry, 2438 North Nottingham Street, Arlington, Virginia. They were brought to the University by James Baylor Blackford, 1511 Palmyra Avenue, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
Patrick Henry Drewry was born in Petersburg, Virginia, May 24, 1875. he attended public schools, Petersburg High School, and McCabe's University School. Drewry graduated from Randolph-Macon College in Ashland (1896) and later received his law degree from the University of Virginia. For a brief time he taught English and Greek at Centenary College in Palmyra, Missouri. Following his admission to the Virginia bar (1901), Drewry returned to his home state to practice law. He was a member of two well-established Petersburg firms: Lassiter & Drewry and Drewry & Old. He also served for a short time as director of Petersburg Savings and American Trust Co.
Drewry always took an active interest in state politics. In 1912, he was elected to the Virginia General Assembly, representing the 29th senatorial district (Dinwiddie County and Petersburg City). Throughout his political career, he enjoyed a favorable reputation as a diligent and competent legislator, and was rewarded for his efforts with the unwavering support of his constituency. As chairman of the Senate Fish and Game Committee, Drewry helped to secure needed legislation to protect Virginia's wildlife. He was well acquainted with state fiscal affairs and served as chairman of the Economy and Efficiency Commission of Virginia (1916-1918) and chairman of the State Auditing Committee (1916-1918). Both agencies exerted considerable control over state finances. In 1919, as chairman of the State Advisory Board, Drewry was instrumental in formulating the Commonwealth's first official budget.
Drewry was continually active in party politics, serving as delegate to several Democratic state and national conventions. In 1923, he was named a member of the Democratic National Committee and later elected as chairman. He held this position for 12 years (1935-1947), longer than any of his predecessors.
In 1920, Drewry was elected to the 66th U. S. Congress, filling an unexpired term. He represented Virginia's fourth congressional district for 27 years. Moderate in his views and quiet in nature, Drewry avoided political controversy, partisan strife, and Congressional spotlights. He served as ranking Democratic member of the House Naval Affairs Committee during a period of rapid naval contracts. He played a key role in the committee's investigation of the Brewster Aero-nautical Corporation which had a government defense contract but failed to satisfy production agreements.
Drewry's voting record in the House was marked with a high degree of party regularity. Despite the dynamic role he played in national politics, he was never considered part of the "inner circle" of the State Democratic Organization. But Drewry was able to capture the confidence of Virginia voters, and was continually re-elected to his post without threatening opposition.
Patrick Drewry was a member of the American and Virginia State Bar associations, Sons of Confederate Veterans, Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Chi fraternities, and Alumni Association of Randolph-Macon College. He also served as a member of the board of visitors to the United States Naval Academy. Drewry married Mary Elizabeth Metcalf in 1906 and had three sons: Patrick Henry; John Metcalf; and William Emmett. He died December 21, 1947 at his home in Petersburg.
Scope and Content Information
The Patrick Henry Drewry Collection (ca. 16,500 items, 23 shelf feet) is comprised of legal correspondence, family financial papers, and some personal correspondence covering the years ca. 1825-1948. Most of the material relates to Drewry's legal practice in Petersburg, Virginia as a member of the firm Lassiter and Drewry (1907-1921) and later during the partnership of Drewry & Old. The collection includes letters from various clients as well as professional correspondence with several prominent Virginia attorneys, i.e.; B. F. Glahn, Samuel Carter, W. R. McKenney. As a member of the Virginia State Senate (1912-1920) and as a U.S. Congressman (1920-1947) Drewry continued to practice law. The letters and papers in the collection reflect Drewry's continuing concern with private legal cases and his commitment to the general welfare of his constituents.
In the initial stages of his career, Drewry focused his professional efforts on settling small property claims and securing veteran benefits for his clients. He also handled a few criminal and divorce cases. The documentation and correspondence concerning a few cases is fairly complete. In 1906, Drewry acted as defense attorney for George Gee, a poor black man accused of murder. Later, Drewry acted as lawyer and friend to Pattie Harris, handling a lengthy legal dispute between Harris and the Virginia State Highway Commission concerning the construction of a road through Ms Harris's property. The Harris Family papers, ca. 1825-1943, make up a large proportion of the Drewry collection.
During his eight years in the Virginia General Assembly, Drewry played an active role in the passage of legislation advancing the State highway system and affecting the Virginia Health Department and the Board of Charities and Corrections. The papers include some information concerning the Vital Statistics Bill (1919) which Drewry helped to formulate.
Drewry was keenly interested in economic affairs and state finances. As a state senator, he served as chairman of the Governor's Advisory Board on the Budget. The collection includes copies of budget documents as well as a few letters for Governor Westmoreland Davis concerning the preparation of the state budget.
As an ardent opponent to statewide prohibition, Drewry worked closely with the Virginia Association for Local Self Government. The campaign for local option is clearly outlined in the correspondence. There are also a few letters concerning women's suffrage.
As a member of the State Auditing Committee and chairman of the Commission on Economy and Efficiency, Drewry corresponded frequently with other officials regarding the financial interests of the state. There is a good deal of information concerning county audits and reports on investigations of various agencies, organization, state schools, hospitals, etc. Drewry also belonged to the Virginia Council of Defense and the Four Minute Men, two patriot organizations established to enlist and maintain public enthusiasm and support during World War I. There are several letters concerning the responsibilities and activities of both organizations.
Although Drewry served as a U.S. congressman for twenty-seven years, there is not a great deal of information concerning his political career in Washington. Drewry corresponded frequently with his secretary, W. L. Bragg, on matters concerning individual legal cases, civil service appointments, private pension claims, etc. There is no significant correspondence between Drewry and his congressional colleagues. There is some information regarding various investigations conducted by the sub-committee of Naval Affairs, state redistricting plans, improvement of Virginia's postal service and expansion of rural routes. There is little material concerning election campaigns or party politics, and only a few personal letters between Drewry and family members.
Organization
Part one of the Patrick Henry Drewry Collection consists of twenty-one boxes and is arranged chronologically. Included are legal documents, business papers, receipts, cancelled checks, social correspondence, and personal correspondence. There is also material relating to Virginia politics, Drewry's campaigns, legislation; patronage, and such controversial issues as woman suffrage and the local option. Although the correspondence in this section has not been systematically organized the material covering politics and Drewry's public career is concentrated in boxes 4-11 and 21. Material covering Drewry's business and personal affairs is interspersed throughout this segment of the collection.
Part two is comprised of boxes 22-29. It contains material similar to that in the first section. It is arranged alphabetically. Among the items of interest are the file on James Cannon and the Local Option Campaign.
There are also two small family collections at the end of the papers. Boxes 48-52 contain the Harris Family papers. Arranged chronologically, this collection is primarily related to financial and legal matters of the family. The A. G. Ryland Papers in boxes 54 and 55 are also arranged chronologically and contain business papers.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1897-1904 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1905-1906 (Box 2)
- Correspondence 1906-1907 (Box 3)
- Correspondence 1907-1911 (Box 4)
- Correspondence 1911-1912 (Box 5)
- Correspondence 1913-1914 (Box 6)
- Correspondence 1914-1915 (Box 7)
- Correspondence 1916 (Box 8)
- Correspondence 1917 (Box 9)
- Correspondence 1918-1919 (Box 10)
- Correspondence 1919-1920 (Box 11)
- Correspondence 1921-1923 (Box 12)
- Correspondence 1924-1925 (Box 13)
- Correspondence 1926-1927 (Box 14)
- Correspondence 1927-1929 (Box 15)
- Correspondence 1930-1931 (Box 16)
- Correspondence 1932-1934 (Box 17)
- Correspondence 1934-1937 (Box 18)
- Correspondence 1938-1940 (Box 19)
- Correspondence 1941-1945 (Box 20)
- Correspondence 1945-1948 (Box 21)
- Correspondence re: Abernathy property and suit 1926-1928 (Box 21)
- Correspondence re: William Barker v. Western Union 1930-1931 (Box 21)
- Letters from Minor Bolling to John Jones 1903-1904 (Box 21)
- Correspondence re: Sale of J. J. Bragg's property 1927 (Box 21)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and W. L. Bragg 1924, 1929-1930, 4 folders (Box 21)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and W. L. Bragg 1931-1932, 2 folders (Box 22)
- Brewster Aeronautical Corp. and H. R. Sub-Committee of Naval Affairs n.d. (Box 22)
- Correspondence and Deeds re: Farm, Old Budd Place 1905-1918 (Box 22)
- Correspondence re: "17 Burge vs. Bishop No. 2" 1920-1927 (Box 22)
- Burton Stock 1933-1937 (Box 22)
- James Cannon 1916 (Box 22)
- Capital cemetery papers 1926 (Box 22)
- Commission in Chancery papers 1925-1927 (Box 22)
- Correspondence re: Committee for local self-government 1914 (Box 22)
- Notes on various deeds n.d. (Box 22)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and H. L. Drewry 1906-1910 (Box 22)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and H. L. Drewry 1911-1937, 3 folders (Box 23)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and H. L. Drewry re H. R. Drewry 1911-1931 (Box 23)
- Checks and receipts on P. H. Drewry's note 1921-1926 (Box 23)
- Military correspondence of P. H. Drewry 1941 (Box 23)
- Correspondence: Address and social work of P. H. Drewry 1941 (Box 23)
- Medical Field School - Extension courses P. H. Drewry, Jr. 1941-1942 (Box 23)
- Miscellaneous - William Emmett Drewry 1931-1938 (Box 23)
- Drewry Family 1841-1883 (Box 23)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Electronic wiring of Drewry home, Petersburg 1925 (Box 23)
- Petitions on Enabling Act 1912-1914 (Box 23)
- Correspondence re: Epstein vs. Epstein 1920-1923 (Box 23)
- Correspondence re: "Four Minute Men in Virginia" 1918, 2 folders (Box 24)
- Correspondence re: Gordon, Pennington & Temple vs. Virginia Henrico Motors, Inc. 1927-1928 (Box 24)
- Governor's Advisory Board on the Budget - Commission on Economy and Efficiency 1919 (Box 24)
- Correspondence re: Helen Green accident 1933-1934 (Box 24)
- Correspondence re: Sale of Griffin's property 1927-1933 (Box 24)
- Estate and Will of Pattie E. Harris, bills and accounts, and notes 1925-1945 (Box 24)
- Papers re: Miss Pattie E. Harris and Pattie Harris vs. Southern Railroad 1926-1945 (Box 24)
- Papers re: Miss Pattie Harris vs. Southern Railroad 1930-1931 (Box 24)
- Papers re: Miss Pattie Harris 1936-1942 (Box 24)
- Papers re: Miss Pattie Harris 1943 (Box 24)
- Correspondence re: John Holcomb Case 1919-1920 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Hollan vs. Rixey 1903-1907 (Box 25)
- Papers re: 1st Judicial Circuit Judgeship 1913 (Box 25)
- Papers re: Settlement of law firm of Lassister and Drewry 1910-1925 (Box 25)
- Papers re: Lassister property 1909 (Box 25)
- Local Option Campaign Correspondence 1914 (Box 25)
- London Naval Conference 1930 (Box 25)
- Papers re: P. H. Drewry vs. Ralph E. Long 1941 (Box 25)
- Papers re: McSweeney, Edward vs. Atlantic Coast Line Railroad 1929-1930 (Box 25)
- Papers re: Bernard M. Meyer vs. P. H. Drewry ca. 1936 (Box 25)
- Papers re: Business with Michie Co. 1924-1927 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Accounts payable to J. A. Minton & Son 1904-1906 (Box 25)
- Papers re: Mahala Mitchell vs. James Mitchell 1923-1924 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: J. B. Parker vs. Western Union 1916-1917 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Perkins vs. Perkins 1920 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: J. W. Perry vs. Narcisia and Ed Bland 1923 (Box 25)
- Correspondence and Papers re: W. E. Pool, sale of property 1916-1921 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Pride vs. Sykes 1921 (Box 25)
- Documents re: Pringos suit 1924 (Box 25)
- Notes on Ragsdale forgery case [1903-1904] (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Collection of Ramey & Son accounts 1905-1906 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Sale of Reams' land 1923-1925 (Box 25)
- Correspondence re: Ridley timber tract 1906-1909 (Box 26)
- Correspondence re: Robinson-Smithey 1927-1935 (Box 26)
- Correspondence re: Robinson Estate [Court] papers-Smithey 1931-1932 (Box 26)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Mrs. P. L. Roper 1924-1927 (Box 26)
- Correspondence and Papers re: P. L. Roper Estate 1932-1935 (Box 26)
- Correspondence re: Sale of Walter Sacks property 1932 (Box 26)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Seaboard Airline Railroad 1929-1930 (Box 26)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Drewry's campaign for Virginia Senate 1911 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Seward Truck & Bag Co. vs. Western Union 1922-1923 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Sledge vs. Charles Hall Davis 1921-1925 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Frances Smith vs. J. Fletcher Smith, Divorce 1931-1937 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Smith & Mercer, Inc. 1922-1923 (Box 27)
- Correspondence re: Smithey bond papers and insurance papers 1926-1935, 1940 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Marvin Smithey - Hopewell property 1926-1932 (Box 27)
- Correspondence re: Southern Sociological Congress 1918 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers: Southside Realty Co. 1911-1921, 2 folders (Box 27)
  See also Box 51
- Correspondence: State Auditing Committee ca. 1916-1919 (Box 27)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Temple vs. Trollinger 1931 (Box 28)
- Correspondence and Papers re: J. G. Turner 1932-1933 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Damage to Drewry's Turnpike property 1933-1934 (Box 28)
- Papers re: Turnpike property 1931 (Box 28)
- Correspondence and Papers re: Virginia Book Co. 1922-1923 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Virginia Council of Defense 1918 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Virginia Highway Contractors Association vs. Dunlop Sand and Gravel Co. 1924 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Virginia National Bank Stock 1930-1937 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals Judgeship 1913-1914 (Box 28)
- Papers re: Volunteer Motor Corps n.d. (Box 28)
- Papers re: Mrs. Ophelia Percival Watson 1928-1934 (Box 28)
- Correspondence: P. H. Drewry and Thomas J. Wertenbaker 1910, 1914 (Box 28)
- Papers: 31.A in re: Western Union, Miscellaneous 1917-1935 (Box 28)
- Correspondence and Papers: Western Union Telegraph [Company files], Fannie Vaughn 1916 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: C. Pool White and Union Baptist Church 1922-1923 (Box 28)
- Correspondence and papers: Archie Wice & Dreyfuss Dress Company 1922-1923 (Box 28)
- Correspondence: William and Mary 1941 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Williamson, C. T. 1925-1926 (Box 28)
- Correspondence and Papers re: C. T. Williamson vs. George T. Temple 1927 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: William T. Williamson vs. J. L. Vaughan and Co., Inc. 1922 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: Woman Suffrage 1919 (Box 28)
- Correspondence re: H. G. Woolworth and Co., Bankrupts 1908-1909 (Box 28)
- Correspondence: Charles E. Worrell 1923-1924 (Box 28)
- Accounts of Herbert Young 1913-1916 (Box 28)
- Checks and receipts ca. 1906-1947, 3 folders (Box 29)
- Newsclippings 1906 and n. d. (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous papers, photographs, blueprints, maps n.d., 4 folders (Box 29)
- Fragments n.d. (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous legal and business papers ca. 1910-1940 (Box 30-33)
- Checkbooks ca. 1935-1945 (Box 34)
- Printed material n.d. (Box 35-45)
- Will of James Harris, Will and Legal Documents of Lewis Harris 1843 & 1865 (Box 46)
- Financial Papers - Harris Family 1819-1844, 5 folders (Box 46)
- Financial Papers - Harris Family 1845-1854, 4 folders (Box 47)
- Financial Papers - Harris Family 1855-1890, 8 folders (Box 48)
- Financial Papers - Harris Family 1900-1919, 3 folders (Box 49)
- Financial and Legal Papers - Harris Family 1920-1943, 4 folders (Box 49)
- Financial Papers - Harris Family n.d. (Box 49)
- Notes of Samuel Westbrook, found in Drewry collection [Harris] 1769 (Box 50)
- Miscellaneous - Harris Family n.d., 11 folders (Box 50)
- Southside Reality Papers 1906-1911 & n.d., 8 folders (Box 51)
  See also Box 27
- A. G. Ryland Papers 1830-1886, 12 folders (Box 52)
- A. G. Ryland Papers 1888-1890, 1895, 1900-1901, 1905 and n. d., 9 folders (Box 53)